Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair;
But I cannot sever the tangled threads on my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Peace to Your Majesty
and the rest of you.
Rise.
I've never seen you
although you've been in the palace for a while now.
So I requested you join us today to meet everyone.
His Majesty knows I'm aloof and unsociable by nature.
So he waived this formality for me.
Even though His Majesty is thoughtful,
how can you not pay respects to Her Majesty,
the head of the harem?
If you truly have respect in your heart,
is it necessary to pay respect every day?
Besides, among all that are sitting here,
whom do we know for certain is not two-faced?
What do you mean by that?
In this harem, who doesn't wholeheartedly revere Her Majesty?
Do you become wholehearted just because you say you are?
You...
Your Majesty, look at Companion Ye!
You're absolutely outrageous!
She's no different from the banished Concubine Sourire.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, I've paid my respects today.
Allow me to take my leave if Your Majesty doesn't have anything else.
Look at her... She...
She hasn't done anything wrong.
What are you mad about?
There...
There has never been someone like this
in the harem - willful and untamed.
There is now.
It's getting late now.
You are dismissed.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Consort Astuce, you stay.
Yes.
Your Majesty,
It was understandable when Concubine Sourire
grew conceited over her favor.
But who is Companion Ye?
She was just an extremely lowborn slave.
How dare she strut around in front of Your Majesty?
Yes, she was born a slave.
She is now His Majesty's most favored woman.
Her status will be elevated
if she produces a prince one day.
It's foreseeable that her status may surpass yours and mine.
How does she deserve to give birth to a prince?
It's likely to happen sooner or later
given His Majesty's favor for her currently.
Concubine Délice said it well:
If only she were ...
infertile!
She would have no offspring to rely on
however much favor she gains.
Do you still remember that you tried to use oleander pollen
to harm Concubine Sourire's unborn child?
Your Majesty, I...
I'll keep your secret since I agreed to do so.
Rather than killing an unborn child with oleander,
taking precautions should be much easier.
Think about my words.
Not for my sake, but for your Third Prince,
to remove seeds of future troubles.
The satin was just awarded by His Majesty.
My Lady, how about choosing the pieces you like
to make into new dresses?
Keep the green and the light blue ones
and you all can take what you like from the rest.
My Lady, all your dresses are either green or light blue.
Would you like to try something red or purple,
which are also beautiful?
I don't like them.
Peace to Companion Ye.
Her Highness Consort Astuce asked me to
bring you a bowl of date soup.
Do I have to drink this?
It is an expression of Her Highness's goodwill.
Go.
Go report to your master.
Your Highness. Your Highness.
You scared me to death.
Why are you being so loud?
I beg Your Highness's forgiveness.
I didn't mean to.
I asked you to wait outside the Hall of Spring Joy
to see what would happen.
Why are you back?
Companion Ye developed a stomach ache.
His Majesty ordered a thorough investigation.
Why is Companion Ye experiencing a stomach ache?
Your Majesty,
I found that Companion Ye had eaten extremely cold-natured food.
This has damaged her fertility.
Therefore, Companion Ye might ...
She is very likely...
What exactly happened to her?
Your Majesty,
It is likely Companion Ye ...
will not be able to get pregnant.
Who did this?
Why did she eat the food?
I ... I don't have further information about this.
The only thing I know is that
her stomach ache would have started right after eating it.
Tell me!
What did she eat before the stomach ache?
Consort Astuce sent Apple here with a bowl of date soup.
My Lady felt unwell after taking it.
Consort Astuce?
Immediately,
bring Consort Astuce to the Hall of Spring Joy.
Yes.
Your Majesty,
officer Zhang Tingyu requests an audience.
What's happened?
He said the floods in the south shattered the dam,
leaving hundreds of thousands homeless.
Where is he?
In Your Majesty's study.
I'm going to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Su Peisheng.
Yes.
Have Consort Astuce closely watched.
I want a detailed explanation from her.
His Majesty departs for the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Were you really the one who did it?
Yes.
The doctors told me that Companion Ye has become barren.
You were quick and efficient.
But His Majesty is not a fool.
Your Majesty,
I was following your instructions.
You have to save me.
Following my instructions?
When did I ever tell you to harm anyone?
You came up with the idea, and you implemented it.
If I could help you, I would be
acting out of the goodness of my heart.
But if I can not,
you have only yourself to blame.
Your Majesty...
I've been protecting you and guiding you
ever since your attempt to harm
Concubine Sourire with oleander pollen.
But what's the use of having a mother like you?
Due to corruption, your father
was banished by the prior emperor.
Since then, you have lost the capability of protecting your son.
If I hadn't been shielding you,
do you think your Third Prince would have safely reached adulthood?
Each time I need you to do something,
you do it with utter stupidity.
When I learned you were stupid enough
to have Apple deliver the date soup,
I knew it would be hard to save you.
Your Majesty ...
I...
Your obvious methods showed everyone you are behind it.
If I continue to protect you,
I'll be dragged down too.
So will the Third Prince.
The Third Prince is not favored by His Majesty
because he has a mother like you.
Tell me,
can you be of any help to
the Third Prince's succession with what you did?
I am a useless mother.
I am so useless.
With a mother like you,
the Third Prince will never become the heir.
I now give you two choices:
The first is that I report to His Majesty that
you tried to harm the imperial heir carried by Concubine Sourire,
and that you poisoned Companion Ye.
His Majesty will also be angry with the Third Prince.
You will be granted suicide
and your son deprived of the chance to accede to the throne.
No, no!
The second is that you end your life of your own volition.
I will help the Third Prince fulfill your wish.
It's your own choice to make.
Your Majesty!
I can't die! I can't!
Please save me! Save me!
I have a son! Save me!
You were foolish in the extreme.
I can't help you.
Also, don't even think about "breaking the net as a dying fish".
If you defame me,
saying that I ordered you to do evil:
One, His Majesty won't believe you;
two, given the Empress Dowager's favor,
my position is unassailable.
You may pray to be blessed.
Third Prince, Mother must go now.
You must accomplish my wishes.
Consort Astuce...
Why would you do such a thing?
She was such a vicious woman,
harboring malice towards others.
Suicide is an escape from justice for her.
Your Majesty, Consort Astuce was just foolish for a moment.
Your Majesty, regarding Consort Astuce's funeral arrangements ...
Consort Astuce committed suicide in fear of justice.
She cannot be conferred honors.
To avoid spreading this around,
and to protect the Third Prince,
I won't investigate further.
She attended me for over a decade and was this foolish!
What a disgrace!
Your Majesty,
Consort Astuce served you for twenty one years.
Consort Astuce is dead.
Even though the Third Prince is an adult,
he cannot be left with no one to look after him.
I am the head of the imperial harem.
I view all the children in the harem as if they were my own.
And I have always taken care of the Third Prince.
I will commit myself to all responsibilites as his mother.
I am relieved to hear you say this.
The Empress Dowager is advanced in years and in ill health.
You have always cherished the Third Prince.
It is most proper that you look after him.
Yes.
Peace to Your Highness.
You need to take care of yourself, don't catch cold.
Thanks.
If you're just here to see me,
you've already accomplished that.
You can go now.
I know you're sad.
But in the harem,
there are many highly skilled doctors.
You will definitely be able to have children.
Sad？Why would I be sad?
You came to visit me
because I was harmed by others,
just like your good sister Concubine Sourire.
You're alike in some ways,
but not others.
It doesn't matter whether I am or not.
Each of our lives is only a breath.
All right. Rest well then.
I won't disturb you any longer.
Even without Consort Astuce's date soup,
I wouldn't want to bear children at all.
I just thought it was odd.
Her date soup was delivered very oddly.
Even my cat smelled something unusual.
Since she eagerly intended to harm me,
I allowed her that.
Whether she added Nine Cold Soup,
or even Crane's Red Crown [poison],
I would not care.
Why would you want to die so badly?
I was free, all by myself.
Who could have known I would be confined here,
gloomy in a sunless cage,
to spend my life with a man I don't even like.
He robbed me of all chances.
What chances?
None of that matters anymore.
I consider it as Consort Astuce giving me closure.
I don't want to bear his children anyway.
Don't say these words to anyone else in the future.
My Lady, Mr. Su is here.
Peace to Your Highness Concubine Vertu.
Peace to Companion Ye.
His Majesty decrees:
Companion Ye suffered from wrongful treatment,
for which my heart grieves and laments.
She is hereby promoted to Noble Lady,
with the honorary name Paix.
This is His Majesty's edict.
I thank His Majesty.
Congratulations, Lady Paix.
Dr. Wen, this way, please.
Mistress.
Good, you're here.
These are new prenatal tonics I prescribed for you.
You can take them for the time being.
Did you not rest well for the last few nights?
Why do you look so unwell?
His Lordship said he would come back in forty days.
But fifty days have passed,
and we haven't heard anything from him.
That certainly worries my mistress.
She had nightmares again last night and didn't sleep well.
I'm afraid that's why she doesn't look well.
But dreams are dreams.
He should be back quite soon.
He won't come back.
What did you say?
Noble Prince Guo will never come back...
He is dead.
Dr. Wen,
you ...
What nonsense did you just say?
How can you curse him like that?
He is the father of my child!
Huan'er...
I have never lied to you because we grew up together.
Noble Prince Guo didn't come back from Yunnan and Tibet...
Not even half a word has been heard by the palace.
His Majesty sent people to look for him
only to find out that his ship had sunk.
They didn't even find his remains.
Mistress.
Huan'er, in the torrential water of the Yellow River,
the iron ship was shattered into pieces.
Even if his remains were found,
they wouldn't be recognizable.
You are talking nonsense!
Nonsense...
Nonsense!
I'm not!
I swear on our years of friendship.
I promise. I'm not lying to you.
He is dead?
I can't even see him one last time?
Huan'er.
Huan'er, calm down.
The deceased cannot be resurrected.
His spirit didn't even reach my dreams.
Huan'er.
What should we do?
Mistress! Mistress!
Huan'er.
Huan'er ...
Mistress.
Why did he die ...
when everything was all right?
Why were his remains not found?
Actually they have found
the wreckage of the ship he was on.
There wasn't any problem with the hull but...
But what?
But the bottom wasn't fastened by iron nails.
It was joined by glue and ropes.
So that once the ship embarked onto the water,
the ropes would break
and the ship would sink.
The vessel was dispatched by the government.
It shouldn't be made like that.
Correct...
There was no problem when the ship was dispatched.
The shipwrights said that
although the hull is the same as what they built,
the bottom is different.
So the ship must have been stealthily tampered with
when berthing on the Yellow River.
Who wants to kill him?
Mistress.
Who wants to kill him? Who?
- Mistress.
- Huan'er, Huan'er.
What's happened has happened.
Who wanted to kill him cannot be known.
Until the body is found,
His Majesty's intention is to not announce his death.
I don't believe it. I don't believe it.
He didn't die!
Mistress.
I don't believe it. I don't believe it.
Dr. Wen, I beg you to say less.
Mistress is with child.
Saying this to her now will take her life!
Haven't you always treated her as your sister?
Why can you not hold yourself back right now?
I really do not want to see her in agony,
waiting for someone who will not return.
Huan'er, I know you feel devastated right now.
But you must be prepared for the future.
Mistress.
If you want to give birth to this child,
I will still let you take the Seven-Day Sedate.
Then Jinxi will report your death.
I will take you away from here.
We will find a quiet place to live our lives in peace.
Rest assured, I will be good to you.
I will treat your child as my own.
I can do everything Noble Prince Guo could do for you.
Dr. Wen,
Mistress won't be able to take in anything you say right now.
Can't you say these things when she has calmed down?
Dr. Wen!
How can you possibly treat His Lordship's child as your own?
How are you able to do the things His Lordship could do?
You cannot compare to him!
As long as I could see him every day,
as long as I could see him smile every day...
No, even if only occasionally...
Even if he wasn't smiling at me,
I would be content.
But now he's gone...
From now on, my whole life,
I will never see him again!
I don't believe it!
Impossible.
You are awake, Mistress.
You were asleep for hours.
Mistress, you've not eaten anything.
You should eat this congee while it's warm.
Dr. Wen said ...
your agitated emotions affected the prenatal qi.
You can't let your sadness overcome you again.
You must put your health above all.
Then... Let me feed you.
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Hongshi bows before Imperial Mother.
Autumn, assist the Third Prince.
Yes, Third Prince.
Third Prince, you shall call me Mother now.
Yes.
I will be your mother from now on.
Although you were not my child at birth,
it is our fate to become mother and son.
I hope we can be "a caring mother and a filial child"
and enjoy a harmonious family relationship.
I will be a filial son, Imperial Mother...
Mother.
All is well then.
Consort Astuce had served His Majesty for twenty one years.
I saw her entering the family as a lord concubine.
And she became a lord consort after giving birth to you.
She was granted the title Consort after entering the palace.
Although she committed a grave offense,
she expanded the imperial lineage after all.
That is a great contribution.
She met a regrettable end, however...
Although His Majesty doesn't agree ...
As her good sister in the harem,
serving His Majesty for years,
I will still remember her as your birth mother.
I will assign guards to protect her catalpa coffin.
I hope she can be at peace underground.
Mother, I am eternally grateful for your magnanimity.
Don't be so grieved, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty has been sorrowing over Consort Astuce for days.
Since the Third Prince has come under Your Majesty's care,
Consort Astuce can rest in peace.
If Your Majesty wallows in grief,
it will sadden the living.
I understand.
But we served His Majesty for years...
How can I contain my grief
when she departed so abruptly like this?
She was an utter fool!
Mother.
I can't make up for my birth mother's offense.
But I will study as hard as I can,
to help carry Imperial Father's burdens.
So I can repay the care and nurturing
from you and Imperial Father.
Very good! Very good!
You are a very good child!
You are my very good child.
What happened? You look preoccupied.
Are you thinking that
I haven't been taking care of Concubine Sourire,
not sending Orchid to see her?
I am just worried about Your Majesty's condition.
When you're old and useless,
life always brings illnesses and misfortunes.
In my current condition,
someone acted without scruple right under my nose.
Once I depart this world,
I'm afraid I will no longer be able to protect any of you.
Causing Your Majesty to speak such sad words
is my offense, and deserves a thousand deaths.
Don't worry.
Each day I'm alive, I will always protect you.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Although Orchid hasn't been visiting Concubine Sourire,
I don't believe the nuns
dare to mistreat her.
Her Majesty the Empress.
You hear ... She makes quite an entrance.
Peace to Imperial Mother.
Not so.
Peace to you, Empress.
The old crone's peace is not the Empress's concern.
Since Your Majesty has taken the medicine, I will excuse myself.
I do not deserve you saying that, Imperial Mother.
I feel nervous and unsettled.
Do you?
I should be the one who feels unsettled.
Your cunning tricks imposed suicide on Consort Astuce
and you took the Third Prince to be your own son.
Fast and efficient!
You are known for clear judgement, Imperial Mother.
But, I did not do that.
Is that not a clear judgment?
Dare you say you didn't cause Consort Astuce's death?
If you insist on saying so, Imperial Mother,
I have no words in my defense.
Of course you don't.
You were so eager to kill Consort Astuce's maid Apple -
pushing her into the lotus pond.
You didn't know Apple was afraid of being mistreated,
so she came to me early on
and told me what she saw and heard.
But it was not me who killed Apple.
Anyway, it's not the first time
you've done such a malicious thing.
How your sister Empress Première died -
you know that better than me.
Since you know this, Imperial Mother,
you should also know that all I've done
is for our Ula-Nara clan.
You should know more clearly than me
that with my sister's soft temperament,
she could not preside over the palace,
or quell the other concubines to maintain balance.
Only I could do such things.
Good! You have the courage to admit what you did.
The two miscarriages
of Lady Joie and Lady Fuca -
the sins you committed are not small in number.
When are you going to desist?
Lady Fuca curried favor with her pregnancy repeatedly.
She didn’t deserve to be the mother of an heir.
If your son were still alive,
you would also compete for favor using your child.
I had a miserable fate.
The First Prince died early.
But I know
the Uya and Ula-Nara families are not the most prominent.
[The Empress Dowager is from the Uya family]
You struggled through all the hardship
to become the Empress Dowager.
And you ensured I would be the Empress
to preserve the glory of our clan.
I've been cautious, even trembling with fear.
All my deeds have been to preserve the prestige of our families.
I am ...
not wrong to do so.
Of course you are not wrong.
I have never been an Empress.
I became the Empress Dowager
when the prior emperor passed away.
So when the emperor gained sovereign power,
I approved of you becoming Empress.
It’s all been to secure the throne of the Empress
in the hands of our clan.
So I turned a blind eye
to many of your wrongdoings.
But the concubines carry in their bellies -
my own grandchildren.
I care more about my grandchildren.
No matter which concubine's son ascends to the throne,
you will rightfully be the Imperial Mother Empress Dowager.
Why must you rush to kill the mother and take her son
in such a ruthless way?
Otherwise there would be two Empress Dowagers in the harem.
Instead of having "two tigers in a fight"
struggling to eliminate each other,
now was a better time to eliminate her expeditiously.
I surely have committed crimes.
But what I have in my heart
is the entire clan of Ula-Nara.
Imperial Mother,
do you think anyone else could possibly
be head of the palace?
I am the only candidate.
And I am the only Empress
who can be "the Mother of the Nation."
However much anger you feel, Imperial Mother,
you must know that granting my own wishes
is also the fulfillment of your own.
Very well! Very well!
"Command an army on your own."
Now you can exert dominance in the whole palace.
I owe it all to you, Imperial Mother,
for your attentive guidance and careful protection.
I am eternally grateful.
You have been sick for a long time
and need not worry about me.
Your priority is rest and recovery,
lest His Majesty again suspect
that Longkodo is the cause of your illness.
You have indeed become ever more like an Empress.
I hope you sit securely on your throne.
But I have to remind you
to always leave room to maneuver.
Complete destruction of your enemies cuts off your own way out.
Thank you for the advice, Imperial Mother.
Just as "Indigo exceeds blue",
I will certainly surpass my predecessor.
Imperial Mother, you can put your mind at ease.
If there are no further matters, I shall take my leave.
Bamboo ...
Look ...
at the daughters I taught.
Première was too soft-hearted,
and Yixiu is too cruel-hearted.
I...
Your Majesty must take more care of your health.
It's not that I don't want to ...
I'm afraid that Yixiu, if set in her ways,
will ruin the future of the Ula-Naras and the Uyas.
My heart hopes that the Empress of the Great Qing
will always come from my clan.
But if no one in the palace can balance her power,
her ruthlessness
will dig her own grave and the graves of
all heirs of Aisin-Gioro [the emperor's clan].
Mistress, where did you go?
You haven't eaten in three days.
Even a man of iron couldn't take this.
Mistress, if you refuse to eat,
you may as well take this medicine.
I asked Dr. Wen to prepare this specifically for you.
It has monkshood, five-leaf akebia, flying-squirrel droppings,
dioscorea, turtle shell, and puncture vine.
These are all effective herbs for removing blood stasis.
Moreover, there is saffron in here.
If you drink this, Mistress,
the concern in your belly will be gone.
You are too devastated to eat and drink ...
The life in your belly can't be saved ...
If you take this medicine,
the unfortunate child will leave you sooner
rather than suffering longer with you.
This medicine is strong and effective.
The child will die with no doubt.
The medicine won't cause you much pain.
You can trust Dr. Wen's medical skills.
Mistress, please drink this.
Huan, my sister! You can't drink this!
You have to save this child.
This is the only heir in His Lordship's bloodline.
You can't abandon him.
Jinxi.
I won't ...
take the abortion herbs.
I want this child.
Not only this child,
I also want my family to be well.
Yunli died.
No one will ever shield me as he did.
I have to learn to protect myself,
and the ones I need to protect.
Mistress, this is the Zhen Huan I know.
I can't die.
For the child in my belly,
for my parents and my family,
and for Yunli, who died unjustly,
I must live.
I must live well.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember, amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.